the science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport play and
life Welcome to perform I'm Andy Galpin
a professor of Kinesiology in the center
for sport performance at Cal State
Fullerton in today's episode we're going
to be talking about the heart and I'd
like to start with a very simple
question and that is why do you
breathe now that may have caught you off
guard and so I'll let you think about it
for a quick second why is it that you
breathe
the first couple of answers probably
rushing to your head are something like
well if I don't breathe I'll die and yes
that's true but
why why is it that if you don't breathe
you'll die with that prompt and you're
now probably thinking about well I've
got to get oxygen into my system because
oxygen is needed as a fuel for
metabolism to produce energy and to keep
my cells and heart and brain
alive well that's not exactly the right
answer of course oxygen is critically
important and you will die without it
but there are many other things going on
that determine how you breathe why you
breathe how often you breathe and why
that's vital to both your health and
performance given that the focus of this
show is to discuss the science and
physiology of maximizing performance I
think it's pretty prudent of us to then
spend a little bit of time learning more
about how and why your heart functions
in order to do that we're going to cover
what I call the three eyes the first
being investigate another way of saying
how do I understand and analyze whether
or not my heart is functioning at the
highest level possible the second eye is
interpretation how do I value those
numbers is that great terrible amazing
best in world history Etc and then the
third one is intervene which is a way to
say what do I do about it how do I
improve various markers how do I reduce
others so that I can maximize my overall
functionality and performance of my
cardiovascular tissue or in other words
your heart in order to do that we're
going to have to expand our conversation
past just the heart itself this is going
to include things like respiratory rate
in fact I opened up the conversation
here by asking you why you breathe and
so we're going to take a look at not
only the cardiac function itself say
your resting heart rate maximum heart
rate cardiac output V2 Max and things
like that but we'll also get into other
important and relative metrics like your
heart rate variability your respiratory
rate CO2 tolerance and other things that
you need to understand to fully
appreciate and then therefore improve
Pro function of your cardiovascular
system before we get started with all
that though we need to take a quick step
back and go through really what the
heart is how it functions what it's made
of and that will then give us insights
and understanding about how to measure
it interpret it and then therefore
improve it now before we go too much
further I'd like to take a quick break
and thank our sponsors because they make
this show possible not only are they on
this list because they offer great
products and services but because I
actually personally love them and use
them myself today's episode is brought
to you by Vitality blueprint Vitality is
the world's only comprehensive blood
work company built specifically for high
performance as we'll cover throughout
the season of the perform podcast a
high-quality blood test is one of the
best ways to better understand your
physiology and areas for improvement
Vitality blueprint uses over 100
molecular biomarkers that are critical
to physical and mental performance then
provides unrivaled interpretation and
Analysis of these data so you know
exactly what's going on in your body
from there vitality's Innovative
software allows you to easily create
clear and highly specific lifestyle
nutrition and supplementation plans
based upon your unique physiology and
goals experience the world's most
premium performance blood work by going
to Vitality blueprint.com
perform I know exactly how dope this
thing is because Dan Garner and I built
it ourselves based upon that system
we've used in thousands of athletes over
the last decade or so so we're stoked
that something that's previously only
been accessible to the world's most
decorated athletes musicians and so on
is now open to everyone let's finally
get you looking feeling and performing
at your absolute best and that starts by
going to Vitality blueprint.com
perform let's go today's episode is also
brought to you by ran ran is a premium
active Weare company that is easily my
favorite in the world few things have AG
gated my wife more than my clothing
choices let's be honest fashion is not
exactly my strong suit partially because
I have just no sense of style but also
because I'm neurotic about texture and
feel so honestly no hyperbole here I bet
she has a 90 plus% return rate on items
that she's bought me in an attempt to
salvage my public appearance but holy
cow did our lives change when we found
ran recently there's not a single brand
I've tried over the years that has the
same quality feel and fit that Ron has
has absolutely mastered ran uses
best-in-class materials to allow their
products to be lightweight and
breathable but still durable enough to
last even when you're training super
hard I remember the first time my wife
wore it for a cycling workout and she
who let's just say is uh well-versed in
the active Weare world was genuinely
surprised by how soft and stretchy but
supportive the material was the Ron
women's collection actually just
launched and is already filled with
great reviews online the rone base
training shorts are brilliant as well
they fit perfectly and have the right
amount of stretch to allow total freedom
of movement they also have pockets which
I like and zippered Pockets that are
sneaky helpful for holding Hotel keys
and things like that the atmosphere tea
and commuter business shirts completely
blew my mind I do not understand how
they made this material I'll never go
back trust me here friends just stunning
craftsmanship all the way around the
wife literally said wow when I threw the
first blue shirt on finding clothes that
meet my texture and feel demands and her
aesthetic requirements have plagued us
for more than a decade but not anymore
thanks to ran if you'd like to try ran
go to ran spelled r o ne.com perform to
get 25% off your first order again
that's ron.com perform to get 25% off
your first order okay the way I'd like
to get started is actually with an
apology you see I I'll admit and I'll
tell you forthright that skeletal muscle
is my favorite um cardiac is a distance
second and I probably spent too many
years not giving the heart is due and
that's honestly because I came from what
would be typically called as an Anor
robic sport background you see I was
much more interested in things like
football a little bit of basketball
baseball and things that require not a
lot of endurance but a lot of power and
so I didn't really necessarily
appreciate in fact I directly said that
the heart was not nearly as important as
your skeletal muscle I've come since to
learn that that was the wrong approach
and I I'll tell you more why even if
you're into those types of activities
you should care deeply about the
functionality of your heart and how that
can absolutely improve your performance
even in situations and scenarios like
that okay so as a quick reminder here
remember your body has three main types
of muscles smooth cardiac and skeletal
now there's a number of structural and
functional differences between these
three and just very quickly smooth
muscle lacks contract off properties and
so some of the things we're going to get
into later the micro anatomy of smooth
muscle it doesn't have and so it lacks
the ability again to contract it can
isometrically hold in place and so this
is really something you don't have
cognitive control over it's the stuff
that regulates kind of um your your
background physiology digestion things
like that cardiac tissue again when I
say that think the heart and skeletal
muscle think everything else so the
muscles you can actively control whether
they be small muscles like in your
fingers eyes or toes large muscles like
your hamstrings or glutes spinal
Erectors and things like that so kind of
everything else is a skeletal muscle now
there's a lot of similarities between
skeletal and cardiac muscle which I'll
talk about a little bit later but
there's also some major differences and
that actually is going to explain a lot
about how you need to approach these
interpret diagnose and then actually
train these things differently and so I
didn't appreciate that earlier in my
career I kind of gave all of the credit
to skeletal muscle and and didn't
understand how important and vital
something like my respiratory rate is in
terms of performance as well as tracking
and monitoring ongoing progress and then
particularly signs of things like
nonfunctional overreaching or
overtraining or general fatigue so I
hope that suffices as a small apology
for all of you heart experts and
efficient AOS out there okay so let me
wind the story back just a little bit so
I can set the stage appropriately and
you'll understand why I felt the way I
did coming out of high school I knew I
was interested in sport performance and
so I actually wanted to go to college to
learn more about the physiology and
science of performance but those
programs really didn't exist and so I
remember being taken on recruiting
visits and they would ask kind of about
your academic interests and I would say
that and they would say well we have an
athletic training program which is
really injury prevention and treatment
and management and stuff like that or
we've got Premed and I didn't want to do
that and really the only kind of
exercise physiology programs involved
exercise but it was really more Public
Health disease prevention treatment
management and stuff like that and so I
never really found a home academically
at least initially so I remember going
through school and again while the
exercise was a part of that it was
really from the perspective of oh yeah
you know athletes do that and then
there's kind of exercise you should park
your car in the end of the parking lot
you should get more steps in and you can
go upstairs and it was kind of that
public health message which is awesome
stuff and Incredibly important it just
wasn't my passion so I kind of remember
almost feeling like I didn't really have
much of a home academically and I would
learn stuff and I was excited about
learning the human body and that stuff
fascinated me and still does so from the
the cardiov ascar perspective I just
really didn't care that much about that
stuff until we got into doing things
like testing the V2 Max I'll tell you
what that is a little bit later and
we'll walk through it but that got my
attention right because it's like hey
this is a maximal exercise test and it
was something we could do for athletics
to see uh who's the most fit who had the
best endurance and if you look at the
research on sport performance there are
some clear associations in fact some of
them are very highly tied to success in
sports in your V2 Max now classically
you would think of something maybe like
an endurance Runner a marathon runner
per se and while the V2 Max is not the
only thing at all that predicts
performance clearly it is higher in
those individuals relative to athletes
in say baseball or golf or something
like that so some sports it mattered a
lot in others it didn't and there was a
way that we could assess and test and
identify performance and it all made
sense to me and I grasped it but what I
never did was make that connection
across to basic physiology and I don't
blame myself because no one else did
either now what's funny about that is it
really didn't come into my purview until
really close to 2010 or so and I was
fortunate enough to as a graduate
student to have a gentleman by the name
of Jonathan Myers a legendary
physiologist out of the University
actually of Stanford and he came and
visited uh our laboratory and he gave a
wonderful talk about the relationship
between VO2 max and mortality and I was
stunned
and now you're talking about and I I'll
give some actual studies later but
you're talking about uh research and
papers that used you 10,000 subjects
100,000 subjects just massive databases
and they're finding incredibly strong
predictions of your V2 Max and how long
you're going to live and my eyes just
exploded and I went that that that's it
oh my gosh being healthy performing
physically at your best is almost the
same thing so now I got really excited
about this metric and said hey man I
want to know what this stuff looks like
what is this is Jonathan the only guy
that found this out well learning more
about the history of exercise physiology
and going back and and I realized we
actually had known this since the late
1980s so there's another legendary
physiologist who unfortunately very
recently passed away named Steven Blair
and he spent the vast majority of his
career running these giant studies the
first one most iconic one came out in a
journal called jamama so Journal of
American Medical Association one of the
preeminent journals in in all of Science
and Physiology and Medicine in 1989 and
in that initial study he was really the
first one that said hey when we look at
V2 Max and we compare that to say
smoking or cardiovascular disease it's
as strong if not a stronger predictor of
how long you're going to live than any
of these other metrics and then actually
if you look at you you you'll see study
after study and you could pull up meta
analyses and and and this has really
caught actually attention the Lexicon
and last say five or so years people
have really jumped on board and it's
it's really warmed my heart actually for
that to happen because I felt like it
was something that Us in the exercise
scientist World a strength and
conditioning folks and again scientists
of exercise have been screaming from the
top of our lungs for 20 years and no one
really paid attention to or cared about
and then people found this stuff out and
started talking about it as if it was a
new finding and us again in our world
we're saying oh my gosh we've been
telling you this for 20 plus years so
that's okay it's a free pass I'll give
you that I apologize to you I will
accept your apology for ignoring us
exercise scientists for so long but I
think it really highlights another theme
of this entire show which is the
importance of understanding what maximum
performance looks like if you want to be
a better athlete that's great it's my
personal interest but that doesn't have
to be yours but the value that creates
to the rest of society is unmatched V2
Max is one of those examples I will
share with you many many more of those
in in another episodes but that is to me
one of the best examples of when we stop
looking at health and performance
differently and start looking at it as
hey if your physiology performs at the
highest level possible you're going to
be healthy right Bill Bowerman if you
have a body you're an athlete and so I
just want your physiology to be
functioning at the highest level that
can you can then choose to use those
skills however you'd like to be better
at playing golf or basketball or
or riding mountain bikes I don't really
care whether you want to have more
energy more recovery better sleep
throughout the day something like a VO2
max is going to be intricately involved
in all of those things now for those of
you that absolutely love numbers I I'll
give you some but please don't get too
specific and particular about these
couple of studies I'm going to go over
think of them just as really highlights
of the overall field depending on which
population is studied in a certain
setting or or database these numbers
will VAR very slightly but again this is
going to represent what you would
generally find across dozens if not
hundreds of similar studies that looked
at V2 Max and overall health and
wellness quick point of clarification
when we say Fitness scientifically we're
referring to V2 Max in the actual
strength conditioning and performance
settings you might have a different
definition of it that's absolutely fine
but scientifically those terms are
pretty synonymous so Fitness means we've
tested your V2 Max in almost every
scientific uh situation so let's start
off with that first seminal Steven Blair
paper from 1989 in jamama in that they
had about 10,000 men and about 3,000
women or so and what's actually
interesting about this study and many
others like it they typically follow the
individuals for years I believe in this
actual study it was something like nine
years and within that several hundred
people actually died and so it's a bit
moreid I understand but it makes the
science incredibly compelling because we
can look at a number of people
wait for several of them to die and then
come back and say what actually was
different between those people who died
at Baseline versus those who didn't die
you know again at Baseline and after
that and so we can get really strong
insights about what predicted death now
what they found in this initial study
and this is directly from the paper
itself was after age adjustment so again
they they would kind of factor in their
age and say let's take that out of the
equation so after age adjusted all cause
mortality meaning died for any reason
declined directly across Fitness levels
so as you reduced your Fitness you
increased your all cause mortality risk
and it went from a number of what is
referred to as 64 so 64 deaths per
10,000 people that was the highest rate
there it reduced from that to about
18.6 and so again if you're looking at
that saying all right if I go from the
least fit category to the most fit my
risk goes from 64 death per 10,000
people down to 18 death per 10,000
people if that part has confused you
just run the 18 versus the 64 so another
way to think about that is if my risk of
dying is 18 and now it all a sudden goes
up to
64 it's a huge increase in your risk of
dying and and nobody wants that similar
story for the women the numbers there
actually went from the risk per 10,000
was
39.5 and reduced all the way to
8.5 and so again clear evidence that
this thing was happening and what's also
interesting here just because someone
will ask I'm sure this was true once
they factored out things like again as I
mentioned age but also smoking habits
cholesterol levels systolic blood
pressure fasting blood glucose levels
parental history of coronary artery
disease and then followup and other
metrics so what they're basically saying
is even if you take those things into
account you still see this massive
reduction in health when we have a
reduction in cardiovascular fitness now
I realize following numbers like that is
sometimes difficult if you're only
listening to this in the audio version
so we will have this paper in the show
notes the actual title of the paper is
physical fitness and all cause mortality
a prospective study of healthy men and
women and again first author Steven
Blair from 1989 so if you Cruise onto
table two of that paper you're going to
see that they actually ran the analysis
and split up the men and women into uh
quintiles so this would mean the lowest
20% of Fitness the next 20 next 20 next
20 next 20 so take everyone across the
Spectrum lowest to highest and split
them up top 20% etc etc all the way down
and what I will read off to you is the
relative risk and again this is risk of
dying as we go from the most fit 20
percentile to the next most fit to the
middle kind of 20% to the second to last
20% all the way to the bottom 20% that's
a way to to view this so if you start at
the highest level of fitness and we put
that as just a number of one .0 right so
this is saying okay you're at a 1.0 if I
go from the top 20 percentile to the
next 20 percentile so think of this as
like 60 to 80th perc if you will my risk
goes from 1 to 1.7 this is a 177%
increase in Risk if I go to the next one
down it's gone from 1 to 1.7 to
1.46 the next after that 1.36 and then
here's where it explodes so again think
of this as if you are somewhere between
the 20th to 40th percentile 100 being
the best zero being the absolute worst
so just being the second to last
category your risk is
1.37 you go from that category to the
body 20th percental so just one category
below your risk goes from
1.37 to
3.44 and this is why people will
highlight you don't have to necessarily
be the fittest on the planet from a
health and cardiovascular perspective
but you cannot be the
lowest the magnitude of improvement you
see from going from the least fit people
around to just a second least fit is
almost half to three times the risk
reduction so massive improvements you'll
see the exact same thing in the women in
in the study so uh to not run you
through everything but we're really
talking about improvements as you go
from the healthiest or most fit kind of
going all the way down to the bottom 20
percentile that risk factor is
2.42 and then the lowest goes from 2.42
all the way up to
4.65 so similar message between the men
and the women just being the bottom of
that category is incredibly dangerous
and problematic for your health so if
you can just do a little bit to bump up
one level that's going to do a lot for
you now again there's a ton of studies
you could pull from here the numbers
again I don't want you to be super
specific on that because they will
differ depending upon the population a
little a bit of context on that I
grabbed another study for you also in
jamama far more recently called The
Association of cardiorespiratory Fitness
with long-term mortality among adults
undergoing exercise treadmill testing
and this is actually going to tell you a
similar story U but wanted to show you
how even the studies that are a little
bit different are are going to have the
same take-home message in this
particular analysis now they've got over
122,000 patients so okay great maybe
there was something unique about Blair
and his little population of 15,000
people or so what about if we 10ax that
number roughly do we see the same basic
results and the answer is effectively
yes so in this almost 14,000 people died
throughout the course of the study so
we're getting same kind of idea pretty
healthy people some are going to die but
what does it really look like in terms
of the folks that stayed alive and those
that did not I'll Zoom you all the way
down to the end to not make it so
painstaking as the previous one but
similar stuff here uh in fact it's even
more jarring because they're able to do
more uh in-depth analysis here of some
of those other co-actors which is what I
want to highlight
so you know directly from the paper
again here the increase in all cause
mortality is associated with reduced
cardiorespiratory Fitness which was
comparable to or greater than
traditional clinical risk factors such
as coronary artery disease smoking and
diabetes now I am certainly not trying
to tell you that as long as you're in
shape that it's okay if you smoke or do
anything else again just from this one
particular study really profound there
right the cardiovascular fitness again
V2 Max was more
predictive than traditional risk factors
like coronary AR disease smoking and
diabetes right so I I'll put numbers
behind this because it gets even more
interesting the cardiorespiratory
Fitness is inversely associated with
long-term mortality and not observed to
be an limit what that also means is
there doesn't seem to be any reduction
in the
benefit by continuing to increase your
V2 Max so in other words the higher your
V2 Max goes the more it seems to
preserve all cause mortality risk so
there doesn't appear to be in this study
in fact you'd see the same thing if you
looked at almost any other study in this
area there seems to be no upper limit
and so there's just really not a
rationale of saying well I'm good enough
here I'm okay this is enough and if I
get any better it won't really help that
much you actually do see that in sport
performance so a classic example here is
in the sport of mixed martial arts if
you to examine the V2 Maxes of the
athletes in that you would see that it's
kind of on an average of about 55
milliliters per kilogram per minute and
if you get past that the benefits of
performance continue to go up but even
but slightly and once you really start
getting past north of 65 it seems to be
really no more association between
improved performance by by that I mean
winning fights doesn't mean it is
detrimental of course or not
advantageous to be in better Fitness
prior to a mixed martial art fight but
we're just saying the rate of increase
in performance against the rate of
increase in V2 Max starts to taper off
we don't see a similar thing with
cardiovascular health I'd like to take a
quick break and thank our sponsors
today's episode is brought to you by ag1
ag1 is a foundational nutrition greens
supplement what's that mean it means
that ag1 provides a comprehensive
variety of vitamins minerals probiotics
prebiotics and adaptogens in an easy to
drink greens powder getting your
nutritional right is hard for many
people I certainly know that I have
clients who really struggle for whatever
reason to get the proper nutrients from
whole food sources now ag1 is not a
replacement for eating highquality Whole
Foods but it is a great foundational
supplement for filling in the gaps where
needed I've also personally found that
with many of my clients ag1 helps move
them just in the right direction for
eating more highquality Foods because it
helps them with Cravings digestion and
many other benefits I especially
personally like taking ag1 when I'm on
vacation or traveling because it helps
me just sort of stay on track with my
nutrition I know that missing a few days
of getting the proper vitamins and
minerals and other micronutrients is not
a big deal at all that's not really how
those things work but for me again I
just like knowing that I'm kind of
staying somewhat on track when I'm
definitely not making the best nutrition
and food choices of my life if if you'd
like to try ag1 you can go to drink
a1.com perform to receive five free
travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2 again that's drink
a1.com perform to receive five free
travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2 okay so hopefully
I've made my point here about the
importance of V2 Max but in case I
haven't just one more final study that I
thought was of Interest here to to bring
this point home even more actually this
is one of Jonathan Myers's more recent
papers called cardiorespiratory Fitness
and mortality risk across the spectrum
of age race and sex published in the
last couple of years here this is
actually in
750,000 US veterans uh between the ages
of 30 and 95 and I like this paper
because the sample size is enormous
again it takes into account things like
race as well as age look at that
Spectrum right almost a 65e spectrum um
and within that
175,000 people or so
died so if it held up against 15,000
then it held up against 150,000 and now
it's holding up against
750,000 I just don't know how much more
evidence one would need to see uh to
believe not only in this as a actual
finding but the relative risk ratio
seems to be lining up across all these
studies as pretty similar and so what
they found in this again same idea they
found no reduced benefit of Extreme
Fitness in other words the higher the V2
Max just the higher the risk reduction
there seemed to be no upper limit
there and in addition what they found
was a couple of metrics so if you take
into account what are called the
comorbidities and so you look at things
like diabetes diabetes in this
particular study took their risk factor
from one to 1.34 so that's a big deal
however going from the highest Fitness
level to the next highest Fitness level
represented an increase of risk of 1.66
so again I'm not saying that diabetes is
okay or anything like that again I'm not
a medical doctor and I don't do really
anything with disease but just look how
staging this is and in fact if you run
this all the way out examples in this
paper and here I'm looking at a figure
two by the way if in case you want to go
look yourself you're talking about uh
the addition of age represented uh a
1.06 increase in risk factor
hypertension smoking arterial
fibrillation Cancer all these things are
plotted you can see how much they
increased risk and all of those the
highest one was chronic kidney disease
which represented
1.49 when you look into the V2 Max
numbers the
lowest risk factor was 1.39 and then it
just escalates from there to 1.66 to 2.1
to 2.9 again with the least fit people
having a 4X higher risk of
mortality that's how important your
heart is and so it's hard for me to make
a cogent argument that even as athletes
who are interested in say again dunking
a basketball or these anerobic high
power low fatigue Sports very difficult
to say your heart is not playing a big
role in your Global health and that that
isn't going to limit your performan and
somehow so at this point if I haven't
convinced you of the importance of your
VO2 max I don't think I can so let's go
ahead and move on regardless now you're
probably interested to know how do I
assess that how do I value that then do
something about it and we're going to
cover that a little bit later I promise
I'll give you a full breakdown of how to
know whether your V2 Max is good based
on whether you're male or female your
age and where that puts you in the
categories and percentiles we'll cover
all those data and have of course plenty
of links directly to tables in the show
notes but I think before we do that we
actually need to talk more about what
makes the cardiac tissue so special and
unique I'm going to talk a lot about
skeletal muscle in other episodes and so
what I want to do here is really focus
on what is unique and special about the
muscle fibers in the heart as this is
going to explain a lot about how we
interpret it what we do about it and how
actually there's more things to pay
attention to than just your V2 Max to
get us started here I'd like to actually
ask you a question that is you ever
thought about why your heart never gets
sore I mean as I said at the beginning
you've got three types of muscle right
smooth muscle which doesn't have
contractile properties and it's not
important IR relevant to force
production or human movement you've got
skeletal muscle which is everything else
it's your arms legs neck shoulders
things like that and then cardiac muscle
your heart now you know when you
exercise really hard or do something
unique and novel train over a larger
range of motion do more Ecentric work
and all these other things your muscles
get sore but why does your heart ever
get sore if you went out right now and
you have an exercised in years and you
ran a VO2 max test you would get
extremely tired but you would not wake
up the next day with a sore heart your
intercostals or your ribs or your low
back or something might be sore but not
your heart well why is that well
actually the answer to that tells us a
lot about how we should assess the
functionality of our cardiovascular
system as well as how we need to think
about training it differently than we
train skeletal muscle you see it always
comes back to physiology right so
there's a reason we're going to walk you
through how the heart is set up the
structure of the fibers why it TRS the
way it does because again this gives us
insights into why we need to totally
change our mindset about how we're going
to train and improve it relative to how
we talked about and we'll talk about
training our skeleton muscle so the
heart is made up of really four unique
areas and we call these Chambers it's
got two at the top called your Atria
your left and right and two at the
bottom called your ventricles and really
the idea is you take blood from the
Atria you squeeze and contract the Atria
that pushes blood into the ventricles
the ventricles in squeeze and that
pushes blood out of your heart and into
your system there's a lot more detail in
there but that's close enough for now of
primary interest is the left ventricle
that's actually the reason why when you
see a heart it isn't that perfect unique
symmetrical shape that you envision when
your 5-year-old daughter draws it it's
actually slightly tilted to the left a
little bit and that's because the left
ventricle itself is larger than the
right ventricle primarily because the
right ventricle just needs to pump blood
to the other side of the heart but the
left ventricle pumps it out of your
heart in throughout the entire rest of
your body down to the tip of your toes
and then all the way back up into your
heart so it has to have enough Force to
have all of that blood movement Up
Against Gravity fighting through
muscular contractions to get blood all
the way to return now you have some ways
that you can help that blood return
along the way but primarily that's what
the left ventricle has to be able to do
and so because it is asked to have a
higher function and know in other words
produce more force it actually is larger
there is an association at all times
between muscle size and muscle strength
though that is not linear and we'll
discuss that in other episodes and so
globally the left ventricle is larger
what's also unique about the heart is
that the way that the muscle fibers
themselves are made up and so you see
your heart like any muscle is just a
composite of many hundreds if not
thousands of individual muscle fibers
and we will talk again about the nature
of those in the skeletal muscle episodes
but for now we need to think that they
are actually quite different and so
while you think of muscle your biceps
muscles or hamstrings muscles or
quadriceps muscles they are meant to
have specific functionality a term that
we're going to use in muscle science all
the time is structure equals function so
the structure the way that it is built
equals the functionality so as a quick
example your hamstring muscles are
primarily meant for explosive movements
to run Sprint jump stuff like that and
so the way that they are built the way
that they contract and oriented and
attached to the B are different than say
your spinal Erectors your low back
muscles that are meant to just keep you
up in vertical all day they're not
really meant to be exploded or contract
with a lot of force they want to be on
and contracted mildly to keep you
vertical and direct with that nice great
posture when we go to the cardiac side
then we need to start thinking okay what
is the actual need and demand of the
heart and so why we want to be able to
turn skeletal muscle on and off a lot
and to have really specific and precise
movement that's not the role of the
heart and fact we need to hedge towards
something else we just want the heart to
contract we don't need it to contract in
different ways we don't need High
Precision we need a full contraction and
in fact more importantly we need to
hedge against the possibility of not
having a contraction if your hamstrings
don't fire appropriately or you think
your glutes are turned off or they're
not as strong as you'd like that's not
going to really change your ability to
live if your heart fails to contract
even one time you have serious problems
if it fails to do that for you just a
couple of minutes you're dead and so the
demand is quite different it needs to be
very consistent and it needs to
basically do the same thing every time
and it needs to have fail saves so some
problem exists it can still contract and
so the nature of the fibers in your
heart are quite different in muscle they
are very very long so you'll see them up
to you know five to six inches in length
of a single muscle fiber in say your
quadriceps they are quite short and
thick in the heart the diameter
cross-sectional area is roughly the same
you're talking about something like 4 to
5,000 micrometers squared in terms of a
cross-sectional area but the length is
very very short now you're talking about
something like 0.1 cm in length and the
reason we want that or the reason that's
actually is happening is because the
fibers themselves are what are called
single nucleated and so this differs
significantly from skeletal muscle that
has know thousands of nuclei in the cell
the nuclei as a quick reminder are the
place in which you hold your DNA it is
the control center of the cell it
determines how the cell responds to
external stimuli recovers repairs goes
through protein synthesis or adds more
mitochondria delet s or whatever the
case may be this is being run by the
nuclei and so by having more of them in
skeletal muscle it allows it to be
extremely plastic and adaptable and
responsive to exercise or interventions
or lack of exercise or anything else
going on on I don't need that in cardiac
tissue fact I don't need it to be
growing and shrinking and dying really
quickly what I needed to be doing is
extremely consistent with both its
Activation so it's contraction and the
force applied in that contraction so the
fact you've got a single nuclei in the
cardiac tissue tells you its primary
role is not actually adaptation in fact
depending on the study you look at
you're going to see that the muscle
fibers in your heart heart are going to
turn over somewhere between 50 to maybe
up to 70% throughout your lifetime
meaning many of the fibers in your heart
that you have as a child especially past
puberty are going to be there the rest
of your life there isn't a huge turnover
now that differs considerably if you
look at something like the skin that's
probably going to turn over you will
have all new skin cells every you know
30 to 50 days or something like that red
blood cells you know may be more like
every 120 days
and you know skeleton muscle can
actually have a a lifespan of maybe a
decade or something like that maybe a
little bit longer but your heart tissue
is going to very rarely turn over it's
not meant to be hyperplastic that does
not mean it doesn't respond and adapt
and change to stimuli like high blood
pressure like exercise it absolutely
does but it happens much slower that's
not the primary job so the fibers
themselves are shorter they are nice and
thick and they have a single nuclei but
they have a couple of actual specially
unique advantages that skeletal muscle
does not have for example they are
connected to each other through what are
called intercalated discs now these are
specific and unique to cardiac tissue
and what actually allows to happen is
for there to be what's called Gap
Junctions so there's almost little entry
points from one of the fibers to the
next one and what that does is it gives
the ability for an action potential
which is the electrical voltage that
goes into the fiber that causes it to
contract it allows that voltage to leak
from one fiber to the next you wouldn't
want this in your skeletal muscle
because that means when you contract one
fiber or set of fibers you might
accidentally contract other ones not
good remember we want High precision and
control of movement in skeletal muscle
with cardiac tissue we just want it all
to go and so the fact that we have these
these open Gates um through these
intercalated discs and through these Gap
Junctions that it says hey if for some
reason we struggle to get intervention
or activation of an action potential as
long as we get it into one of the cells
it'll be able to leak into the rest of
them as well so in this case we want to
hedge guaranteed contraction Over
Control now on a similar point if you go
to skeleton muscle it exists in what are
called motor units so you might have
several hundred to even many thousands
of muscle fibers all inated or
controlled by one basic nerve is the way
to think about that okay this allows you
again to upregulate how many of your
muscle fibers in your muscle are
Contracting at a given time by turning
on or off more total motor units the
heart doesn't have any there's no motor
unit in the heart we don't want to have
the consequences of what if a nerve
fails or is blocked or dies and now we
can't contract those fibers and so in
fact the heart is not dependent upon
nervous system activation to contract
now I'll say that again the heart does
not require any nervous system
activation to contract and this explains
exactly why you can do really awesome
and interesting things like in the movie
Indiana Jones Temple of Doom where the
gentleman reaches into the guy's heart
and he pulls it directly out of it and
he stares at that man's heart that's in
his hand and it still continues to beat
this happens because again unlike
skeletal muscle which requires nervous
system activation the cardiac tissue
does not it has it own intricate rate
and can spontaneously uh produce the
electricity needed to contract
independent of the nervous system now
that does not mean the nervous system
does not have a role in your heart it
absolutely does and we're going to talk
a lot about that in fact it's incredibly
important to understand that as a way to
monitor Global fatigue Readiness
performance and overall nervous system
activation another thing that
differentiates the skeletal from the
cardiac tissue is how and how long they
contract in skeleton muscle we actually
want the ability to do what's called
summation to reach tetany and so what
happens is the muscle fibers in say your
biceps brachi will contract with that
electrical potential and then actually
almost before it gets all the way back
to Baseline it will contract again and
then it'll contract again it contract
again and so those those Min
contractions start to stack on top of
each other or summate and in fact if you
do that long enough you can reach what
is called Full tetany think of this as a
muscle cramp so this is the muscle
fibers themselves Contracting
permanently instead of doing this kind
of on off on off Rhythm cardiac tissue
doesn't do that and I think you could
probably imagine why it would be a very
bad thing for you to reach tetany of
your heart remember when we first
started talking about the anatomy of the
heart the primary job of the heart is to
move blood from the Atria or the top of
the heart to the ventricles and the
bottom and then move that out to the
body so if this thing were to reach
tetney blood wouldn't move anywhere you
wouldn't be able to circulate any blood
throughout your body and of course you
would die so while it's okay to have a
cramp in your calf and it's painful and
it's annoying and it's all those things
having a cramp in your heart would be
far worse and so your body Hedges
against that and what it says is all
right if I have this extremely fast
what's called refractory time in
skeletal muscle it's the ability to kind
of contract multiple times and then a
single muscle
fiber I want to extend the time of
contraction in the cardiac tissue so
that I don't have that repeat and
summation so in addition to not wanting
tetany you also need to allow time for
blood to fill up the ventricles remember
this we're going to come back to this
later in the episode when we talk about
determinance of V2 Max what to improve
in some of these these other numbers and
why that relates to your resting heart
rate your maximum heart rate why that's
not trainable why there's no difference
in maximum heart rate between highly fit
people and unfit people and things like
that so the ability of your heart to
fill back up with blood is critical so
it's got to contract allow enough time
for blood to fill back into the Atri or
ventricle and then contract again so big
long smooth contractions not a lot of
plasticity in the tissue itself we want
to hedge against having lots of fine
motor control we want consistency over
specificity here so another way to build
on top of that is going back to what I
said a second ago how does it produce a
contraction independent of the nervous
system I gave you the potentially little
bit crude example from uh the Indiana
Jones movie but another way to think
about this is how can my heartbeat if
I'm unconscious right if I've got the
brain turned offline well it will
continue to do that because it has this
intrinsic rate you've got four what are
called Pacemakers in your heart the one
I want to cover and talk about the most
is the SA node so the Ceno atrial node
this is in the right Atria and it
controls for the most part your heart
rate now you've got other ones like the
AV node penji fibers and uh bundles of
his and things like that but those are
really backup systems so in case the SA
node fails it'll go to the next one go
to the next one and all the way down
there so we've got various fail safes
that give us the ability to say all
right if we have a problem we're still
going to get contraction because
remember all we've got to do is get one
chunk to Fire and it'll spread through
those Gap Junctions and get everything
else to contract in the appropriate
fashion and so we want to have that in
position this is also why if you have
something like a heart attack and
several of your tissue in your heart die
you can still survive because you can
get contraction of everything else but
it is complicates the process right
because we start to lose electrical
impulse through the parts of the tissue
that are dead now the essay note itself
is actually a bit of a Marvel you could
sort of think about this and actually
remember in school being told that we
have no idea it's one of the modern
Mysteries of the world of how the essay
note intrinsically develops this pace
well that's not exactly true I think my
teach they didn't know the answer or was
just trying to hypee me up a little bit
we know a lot more about what controls
it in fact there's a number of things
that go into that it does have a little
bit of Wonder I don't want to steal that
we don't know exactly how or why this
thing beats the way it does why it's
similar between almost every human and
how it can just spontaneously create
these Action potentials that is
regulated by a number of things
including uh various endocrine or
pericine um these hormones that are
circulating in your system blood
pressure the strength of your
contraction the amount of blood that
comes back into your heart called
preload and various other factors so
it's actually a fairly complicated millu
that go into it I'm actually still okay
with you thinking about it as this
modern mystery that has just this
magical property where it contracts and
causes electral stimulation and action
potentials out of nothing I'm cool with
that too what we do know more about
though is how this regulates the rest of
your body so when we talk about skeletal
muscle we know specifically there's a
neurotransmitter called acetylcholine
that is required for muscle Activation
so the reality of it is your nerves are
actually not directly attached to
skeletal muscle there's a little space
in between them what happens is
acetylcholine is on the pre synaptic
nerve so this is the nerve that comes in
there it gets released into this little
space in between actually attaches to
little Lian Gates on the muscle itself
they open up they let sodium and into
the tissue and they cause a whole series
of electrical things we call this an
electrical to a chemical backround
electrical signal way you transfer an
electrical signal down your nerves into
a chemical signal back into an
electrical signal that allows muscle
contraction so once again acetyl choline
is the primary neurotransmitter that
excites or activates skeleton muscle but
shocking
enough if you put acetylcholine onto the
heart it slows it down yeah it does the
exact opposite and so you have a number
of nerves that are coming in probably
the most famous is the Vagas nerve now
this is a v Aus not a v gas like the
city so the Vegas nerve and several
others are what are known as
parasympathetic drivers and so the
autonomic nervous system is split up
into two large branches the first one is
the parasympathetic this is rest and
digest this is relaxed sleepy depressed
chilled all those things over there
right the other side of the equation and
it is more complicated than this but
this is all we need to know for right
now is the sympathetic this is fight or
flight this is freeze this is action
anxiety aware aroused and all kinds of
things like that we want both of these
they are critically important for
everyday life we need these for high
performance we need these for health we
need these to just be alive and so we
want to be able to fluctuate back and
forth between these two states
appropriately they are not onoff switch
they are more like a gradient or a
toggle they're they're a dimmer switch
more so than they are you know again
flipped on or flipped off so what
happens is the intrinsic rate of that SA
node
is probably higher than your resting
heart rate in fact it probably wants to
beat more like 100 to 120 beats per
minute most people's resting heart rate
is more like 60 to 80 beats per minute
so you kind of have this vagus nerve
that is constantly applying this drip of
aceto choline to naturally slow your
heart rate down now this is actually
really cool mechanism because what
allows you to do is if you want to
increase your heart rate the very first
thing you have to do is not necessarily
turn on sympathetic
drive it's just to reduce
parasympathetic drive another way to say
that is imagine you're driving downhill
say you're in San Francisco or some
place that has a ton of hills and you're
going at 60 M hour and you decide you
want to go faster well the initial
instinct is to maybe hit the accelerator
or hit the gas think of that as the
sympathetic nervous system well you
don't actually have to do that the first
step is just to make sure your foot
isn't on the brake the parasympathetic
nervous system so kind of what's
happening is at all times when you're
driving the Vagas nerve is slowly
keeping its foot just a little bit on
that brake to keep you relaxed now it's
doing that again so that if you want to
go faster really quickly all we have to
do rather than giving out additional
resources like epinephrine or adrenaline
all I actually have to do is stop us
from slowing you down it's kind of one
of those classic double negatives right
so if I inhibit the inhibitor I can
actually go faster so if I remove my
foot from that break my heart rate will
increase to again somewhere in that 100
to 100 20 beats per minute range plus or
minus here without us doing anything if
I want to continue to accelerate past
that so now I'm going down that Hill I
was going 60 M an hour I've removed my
foot from The Brak now I'm going 80 M an
hour or 100 miles an hour but that's not
fast enough I want to go 150 now I can
hit the accelerator now I can push down
on the sympathetic nervous system
increase adrenaline turn on a faster
rate and pump my heart even more to
produce more work more energy or
whatever I'm trying to accomplish
great now that we've got that down let's
go back and answer our question why
doesn't the heart get sore well let's
think about it what are the reasons that
cause skeletal muscle to get sore
remember all skeletal muscle with the
exception of one and I wonder if you
know that which one that is by the way
all skeleton with the exception of one
is connected to Bone via tendons and so
when we contract muscle connects pulls
on the connective tissue pulls on the
bone to get you movement our
cardiovascular our heart is not that it
is not connected to Bone that's not the
point we're not trying to cause movement
it is really just connected to itself so
because of that we can't ask it to go
over any additional range of motion so
that factor gets thrown out the only
thing we can possibly do is put more
blood back into the heart which puts it
on an Ecentric stretch that's our only
mode here now Ecentric exercise does
lead to excessive soreness if done
especially heavy or in a novel fashion
with traditional exercise and so
Ecentric exercise is something to pay
attention to but the fact is we don't
have the ability to overload the heart
more than the maximum amount of blood we
already have in our system so there's no
novelty we can add to it that it's not
already used to by the way to answer
your question what's the only muscle not
directly attached to Bone I give you a
hint you can see it on me right now and
if you were my 5-year-old you would love
to show it to me all the time it's your
tongue pretty cool right all right going
back to business here
so it's not range of motion it's not the
Ecentric training other things that
cause soreness are higher intensity not
really applicable here again if you're
used to Contracting at a maximum heart
rate we're not going to be able to go
past that more volume well we could do
that but more volume tends to mean more
exercise over more range of motion your
heart beats all day it is not subject to
that much change in volume if you looked
at the total amount of heart beats that
you go through throughout the day a
little bit of exercise is not changing
that volume too much so it's really
difficult to add much volume relative to
the standard or Baseline there and so as
you just continue to go down all the
other factors that influence muscle
soreness and you see they don't really
apply to muscle again that's not its
primary role and so while you may get
fatigued from exercise especially
endurance-based exercise the heart
itself is not really subject to fatigue
in fact the heart rarely gets tired it
has far more mitochondria in it than
skeletal muscle we used to refer to this
as the ultimate slow twitch muscle it is
not meant for force of contraction going
back to motor units we actually can't
alter force of contraction in the muscle
fibers themselves in the heart we can
only do it by changing the stretch on
the tissue same thing in your skeletal
muscle but in that case you've got both
options right change stretch or strange
contractile properties we really can't
change the contractile properties in the
heart especially acutely what we can do
is put it on more stretch this means
more blood back into the system again
preload we'll talk about that a little
bit later afterload is another way but
if if we put more back into it we put
the muscle on a bigger stretch and this
allows it to then respond I think about
like a rubber band if I pull it a little
bit it snaps back if I pull it a lot it
snaps back harder that's all we can
really do but it is not meant uh to be
regulating Force up and down we don't
even have motor units it's an all or
none thing ideally and so we've got a
lot of mitochondria in there we are
phenomenal at aerobic metabolism again
specifically within the contractile
properties we're not talking about
aerobic metabolism of your entire system
or heart we're talking about about the
capillaries surrounding the heart itself
the ability to get blood into the tissue
of the heart not the blood actually in
the chambers that you're using to send
the rest of your body remember your
heart has its own blood supply not the
stuff it's trying to give out to
everybody else um think of this like as
Halloween where you've you're sitting in
a house and you've got this giant bucket
of candy and the candy you're giving out
to the rest of the world you're not
eating that candy as well you've got
another supply of candy in your back
pocket and in your house and you're
pulling out of that candy if you will
okay so the hardest self is meant to be
incredibly robust against fatigue
against damage against soreness and
against changing any of that's inherent
contractile or ionotropic is what the
cardiovascular folks would probably call
it properties that said it does respond
somewhat similar to skeletal muscle with
exercise adaptation so just like in
skeletal muscle where you can add
quality contraction force and speed and
power and you can add quantity muscle
size the same thing actually happens in
the heart the heart can get physically
stronger this would result in you
pumping out more blood per pump again
the fibers themselves won't necessarily
change their inert properties but the
heart can contract with more Force we'll
talk about that a little bit later
that's going to be referred to as
ejection fraction and stroke volume it
can also get larger and in this
particular case typically what you'll
see in response to exercise or healthy
lifestyle behavioral changes the
enlargement in your heart you'll see
will be primarily in the left ventricle
again this is the one that's going to
have to deal with the pressure of the
aorta getting that blood out the rest of
your body and what will ideally happen
is the amount or size of that chamber so
the the inside the amount the space that
can be filled by Blood will either stay
the same or even get slightly bigger but
what you'll basically do is you'll pack
on tissue to the outside of the
ventricle so it gets bigger allows it to
produce more Force but it doesn't
compromise the size of the chamber so
again think about the left ventricle as
a balloon if that balloon gets smaller
and you can feel less blood in it that's
going to be a problem we don't want it
to necessarily be extremely large either
and so if the back end grows but the
chamber size the balloon size stays the
same then we're going to be able to
contract with more force and not
compromise our total blood flow if you
achieved an adaptation like that and it
allowed you to pump out more blood per
pump that number is called stroke volume
so the volume of blood that comes out
per stroke or per contraction the
percentage of the blood that gets
emptied out of that ventricle is called
your ejection fraction so let's just say
there was 100 milliliters of blood in
your left ventricle and you contracted
and 50% or 50 milliliters was left in
The ventricle your ejection fraction
would be 50 and so we would like to see
high ejection fractions so that we're
not wasting our time Contracting and
blood's still sitting in a
ventricle if you improve either of those
things and I'm going to really focus
mostly on stroke volume here that will
allow your heart rate to drop and so one
of the classic adaptations we see of any
type of physical training but think more
specifically endurance type training is
a reduction or a drop in resting heart
rate see at rest right now as you're
sitting here listening the amount of
oxygen
required is the same whether you're fit
or unfit it doesn't necessarily matter
there's a minimum amount of oxygen based
on your body size and other factors that
don't really matter your Fitness level
and so we call that your cardiac output
okay so what that is is it's the stroke
volume multiplied by your heart rate so
how much is coming out per pump and how
many times are you pumping in a given
minute you multiply those together and
you get a cardiac output let's just say
that number is 5 lers per minute it's a
very standard resting cardiac output if
if you are fit and we improve your
stroke volume since the total demand
again the back end of this equation is
still five lers per minute but I've
increased one of the numbers that allows
me to decrease the other number and so
your heart rate as I said the SA node is
paying attention to many things and one
of them is that preload so how much
blood is coming back in and how much is
going back out and various other factors
so it knows if I'm getting say this 100
Millers of Blood Out per
pump I don't have to pump as often so
increase the acetylcholine drive slow
the heart rate down and let's chill out
in fact we we'll cover some of these
numbers later about uh what a good heart
rate is what the best we've ever seen
why you don't want to be too high or too
low and stuff like that but that's
basically what's
happening and so we can identify whether
or not we're struggling in either the
stroke volume portion the cardiac output
side of the equation or heart rate just
based on that understanding of how the
heart works that will then tell us what
style and type of training we need to do
to make the most efficient improvements
and not only our heart rate but more
importantly our V2 Max now your heart
rate again how many beats per minute
you're using at rest or during exercise
is incredibly telling as I mentioned
earlier it doesn't actually change
though in response to exercise training
at its maximum the only really thing
that matters in this particular case is
your age and we know that maximum heart
rate goes down as you get older but it
doesn't alter that much with Fitness and
so what it can tell you though are
things like your heart rate variability
and so let's just use the example of a
heart rate of 60 beats per minute so one
would think and assume that if my heart
rate is 60 beats per minute that means
I'm having 60 beats in 60 seconds that
would be one beat per second and if you
calculated the total amount of Beats you
had over the course of the minute you
would in fact achieve 60 that's what
that number means but it doesn't
necessarily mean it's on the exact same
Rhythm so it would not be like on a
metronome your heart would not be
beating every second on the second there
is a
variability in the space between heart
beats so while you again you would
achieve the same number by the end of
the minute in this case 60 it might do
two or three fast ones in a row have a
little bit of a pause have a little bit
of a pause a fast one five fast ones Etc
so there's a variability in that rate
now it's not very long it's actually so
small that you won't even be able to
perceive it but we can measure this with
a number of different Technologies this
is called heart rate variability you may
have heard of it before it's been around
for over 60 years and there's extensive
evidence and research on this originally
most of the work there again came from
these disease and health models HRV has
been associated with cardiovascular
Health
mortality mental health depression
anxiety but more importantly for me was
when HRV started coming along for things
like athlete Readiness recovery sleep
and performance and so as always the
case physiology is physiology friends if
it's dysfunctional it's dysfunctional if
you're leading that to long-term Health
implications if that's leading to
short-term performance detriment it's
really the same thing right so
understanding the role of HRV is
something we're going to have to get
into a lot later in future episodes I
would love to talk to you more about
that there's a lot of nuance and
interesting things we can pull there but
globally something we want to pay
attention to so as we go into our next
section here where we cover those three
eyes right how do I investigate my
current cardiovascular fitness how do I
interpret how good that is and then how
do I intervene what do I do about it I
want to make the point that just looking
at your video to Max is not enough just
looking at your resting heart rate
wouldn't be enough you would also want
to pay tremendous attention to your HRV
and then various other factors like your
respiratory rate again I'll do
respiratory rate in a future episode I
would love to talk to you for many hours
about that I would actually tell you
right now a little bit of a spoiler
alert I think that is the most
underappreciated of all these metrics I
think it should be considered a Vital
sign and is potentially the most
important thing that you can measure for
overall fitness and health and quite
honestly it's the thing I pay the most
attention to on a day-to-day basis of
all of these metrics more on that later
you're gonna have to wait for now though
I'd like to take a quick break and thank
our sponsors today's episode is brought
to you by momentus momentus makes safe
highquality supplements now I naturally
despise and frankly don't trust most
supplement companies and for good reason
in fact I recently co-authored a review
article that was published in 2023 in
which we found that the amount of
adulterations which accidental
contaminants or deliberate spiking like
adding stimulants or anabolic or other
agents which are not supposed to be in
the product or mislabeling in which the
supplement contains either a far greater
or lower concentration than is being
reported on the label is shockingly high
so I actually honestly spent literally
years vetting both momentus and their
leadership team before deciding to
officially partner with them last year
bringing them on as a sponsor for the
show was this a natural ution of our
partnership now I did all that because
of their dedication to cleaning up the
supplement industry and I've seen them
do that with their pocketbook first
every single momentous product is third-
party tested and that's expensive and
many are even further NSF certified for
sport but more unique than that is their
vision for the future of where this
frankly dysfunctional industry should go
for example they've recently started an
initiative they called the momentous
standard which I can't wait to tell you
more about down the road on top of this
strong ethical company value their
products are also fantastic they're used
by the best of the best including
countless professional teams Olympic
committees 31 of the 32 NFL teams many
members of the Department of Defense and
many more now none of you have to use
supplements and I genuinely hope you
never feel pressured to do so if you
don't want to and supplements will never
be more important than Whole Food
and I've had great success with plenty
of athletes and executive clients who do
not want to use any supplements for
whatever reason however they can be
beneficial to some so if you're going to
use them I strongly encourage choosing a
brand like momentus which in my opinion
has the highest safety and quality
standards in the world if you'd like to
give momentus a try go to
live.com perform to get 20% off your
order again that's liv.com perform
to get 20% off today's episode is also
brought to you by element element is an
electrolyte drink mix that has an ideal
ratio of sodium potassium and magnesium
but has no sugar electrolytes are
critical to proper hydration which I've
been harping on for years but you can't
do that by only drinking water in fact
many of you will probably remember that
I featured element in my YouTube series
on optimizing hydration all the way back
in 2020 which is obviously long before
this podcast even existed so I've been a
fan of element for a long time in fact
astute listeners will also realize these
hydration videos were the Genesis of the
Galpin hydration equation named not by
me but by the legendary neuroscientist
Dr Andrew huberman I featured element in
these videos because their blend of
1,000 Mig of sodium 200 Mig potassium
and 60 Mig magnesium really is different
than any other electrolyte on the market
and has great scientific support however
I want to be ultra clear 1,000 Mig of
sodium is a lot and not everyone needs
that much in fact that may be way too
much if you don't exercise or sweat much
already eat a lot of salt in your diet
say from a lot of processed foods or
otherwise have sodium related medical
concerns I personally use the Citrus and
watermelon flavors a ton to preh hydrate
before heading out on a full day of
training or long hike or a hunt since I
know I'll be losing a bunch of fluids
and won't have many opportunities to
take things with me element has also
just released a new line of canned
sparkling element which I am all about
if you'd like to try element you can go
to drink LM nt.com perform to claim a
free element sample pack with the
purchase of any element drink mix again
that's drink LM nt.com perform to claim
a free sample pack okay we're now at the
part of our conversation where I can
answer the question we started off with
which is why do you breathe and we
talked about how it's oxygen and we need
that well oxygen is not really a fuel
for metabolism it's needed to go through
aerobic metabolism but the fuel is
coming from your fat and carbohydrates I
only need oxygen during aerobic
metabolism but I'm very effective at
anerobic which means I can produce
energy without the need of oxygen but to
finish those processes I've got to have
the oxygen around and so it's a little
bit of a Twist here this is also
explaining why even if you're an
anerobic athlete you still care deeply
about your Aerobic System because this
is what allows you to recover to
completely metabolize your carbohydrates
to finish that process and restore
yourself back to homeostasis the faster
you can do that the faster you can
repeat your Anor robic processes you can
recover you can get back to training get
back to competition the more you
practice the better you get the better
you perform and so what's actually fully
happening is this when you take a breath
in and you inhale you're bringing in
amongst other things but primarily
oxygen when you take a breath out you're
breathing out CO2 the oxygen you bring
in is primarily there to regulate
metabolic processes but the CO2 you're
exhaling is regulating your pH now
there's a handful of things your body
will regulate almost anything else one
of them is your pH it does not like to
mess with this if you were to look at
other markers like say your blood
glucose you realize that that's highly
variable it can be as low as you know 70
milligrams per deciliter as high as 150
during exercise or something like that
and so you can see it all double or
maybe even triple the amount in the
blood you would never do that with ph it
has an extremely tight window that it
will not move out of that's because all
the enzymes that are required for you to
go through any metabolic process need to
be in a certain PH range if it gets out
of that becomes too acidic or too
alkalic they can't function you can't
create energy you're going to die very
very quickly so pH is insanely important
to hold into a tight window and so what
happens is you don't feel that air
hunger or that desire to breathe because
oxygen starts getting low remember
especially at rest or even during
exercise you can produce energy anob so
when you start getting low on oxygen
you'll just switch to anerobic catm it's
not necessarily a reason for you to
panic to stress or to change your
behavior increases in CO2 though will do
that and so remember your muscle is
whether it's using fat as a fuel or
carbohydrates as a fuel it's trying to
generate a molecule called ATP this is
the energy currency in all of biology
and it doesn't matter what you use that
ATP for by the way it doesn't matter if
we're talking about skeletal muscle
we're talking about cardiac muscle or
anything else so whether you're using
this for exercise to power your brain to
recover to digest food it's irrelevant
here right we're going to use
carbohydrates or fat as a fuel we're
going to make ATP and then at the end
the final B product of all metabolism is
going to be water CO2 and ATP so the CO2
concentration increases as metabolic
rate
increases as a result of that you start
then moving CO2 from your tissue into
the blood concentrations of CO2 then in
blood go up you've got chemo receptors
in your brain stem and various other
places that are going to be paying
extreme attention to the amount of CO2
in your blood if CO2 gets really really
high we call this hyper Capia if it gets
low it's called hypo Capia remember
those terms so hypercapnea increases in
CO2 concentration actually signal your
red blood cells to drop the oxygen on
them making it easier for your muscle to
extract and absorb the oxygen
effectively think about it this way if
CO2 is high in the blood your body is
under the assumption you're going
through a lot of metabolism so it's
under the assumption that we want to use
and need a lot of oxygen so it reduces
that affinity and this is called the
bore effect if you get hypocapnic again
too low of CO2 it does the opposite now
this is going to be
counterintuitive when we talk about
things like CO2 tolerance and
respiratory rate in in future episodes
as to why you could potentially have
problems with hyperventilation or over
breathing so what's happening in this
context is those signals are being sent
to your brain and that is interpreting
it as saying CO2 is too high let's
reduce that the way you reduce CO2
concentration in your blood is to Exhale
and so this would cause you to increase
your respiratory rate and to start
either mildly or excessively
hyperventilating and this is why as you
exercise your respiratory rate again the
amount of breaths you're taking goes up
it is in part to increase and bring in
oxygen of course but when we're doing it
Anor robic we're not using oxygen
anyways so the real reason we're
breathing so hard and we're panting and
and all that stuff is we're getting
harder and harder of our exercise is
because we're trying to dump and get rid
of all that CO2 buildup remember excess
CO2 is altering pH this is making us
more acidic this becomes an extreme
problem
so another way to think about this is
when you
inhale that's actually a sympathetic
driver and so your heart rate increases
during inhalation when you exhale it is
parasympathetic and it drops so
effectively what's happening is your
body is sort of saying oh you're
inhaling we're assuming then you're
bringing in oxygen let's get prepared to
deliver this oxygen throughout the
system when you're exhaling it's the
opposite I don't want to be in a situ
situation where I'm hyperventilating I
don't need to be breathing too much
because if again that CO2 gets too low
instead of being acidic we are now in
respiratory alkalosis so the opposite
direction right we're too basic and so
it slows the heart rate down so every
time you take a breath in your heart
rate jumps up a little bit every time
you take a breath out it goes down a
little bit so if I'm altering my
respiratory rate I'm then altering my
heart rate and this is why things like
HRV are so intrinsically tied to things
like respiratory rate I can't let us
move off this point without saying one
final thing I know we want to get to our
three eyes here in one second but a lot
of people are aware and in the coaching
world people use HRV very often and
there's a lot of data to support this
there's a lot of critical information we
can get for assessing say exercise
volume fatigue Readiness and things like
that tons of value there but I don't
think enough people are paying attention
to respiratory rate this is really
highlighted in a paper that just came
out in the last few months and so I'd
like to bring this to your attention
what they did is looked at College age
students and they simply measured their
respiratory rate and one of the things
that they found that's interesting is
for every
breath per minute that increase so if a
respiratory rate went from 15 breaths
per minute to 16 breaths per minute they
increased their likelihood of experien
stress by
1.25x and what I found particularly
interesting about this is they found
that
irrespective of changes in things like
HRV total hours of sleep sleep
efficiency sleep onset and various other
things that are typically the metrics
used to measure overall stress and
autonomic nervous system functionality
and things like that and so what we're
what we're going over here is not to say
that HRV or sleep are not good metrics
to take they clearly are it's just that
you're going to find things in the
respiratory rate that you're not
necessarily going to see in other places
that give you great clues about overall
stress so strongly encourage you to pay
attention to respiratory rate and we'll
talk about that plenty in the future so
at this point we've now got a much
better understanding of why our
cardiovascular system matters to both
performance and health we know a little
bit more about how it contracts with
some of the unique properties that exist
within it that differentiates it from
some of our other tissue like skeletal
muscle and then of course we've learned
why we breathe and how that relegates
many other functions like our sleep
recovery and of course overall
performance using all that we can now
discuss the three eyes which are how do
I investigate how do I interpret and
then how do I intervene on improving my
cardiovascular fitness let's start with
the first eye investigate now depending
on the metric you're interested in
something like a heart rate can be done
with no technology whatsoever you can
simply put your fingers up to your neck
count your heart rate divide that by the
time domain and get your heart rate easy
example there most classic one we teach
is start a stopwatch count how many
times your heart beats in 15 seconds
multiply that by four and then you'll
understand how many beats you're taking
per minute you could also simply just
measure it for one minute count those
numbers and that's fine but in reality
most of you probably have some sort of
Fitness technology app or watch or
something of that sort that's going to
tell you that number already as far as
things like HRV and respiratory rate
we're going to have to cover those in
their own IND idual episodes as you've
got a lot of options and there's some
context there I will tell you again most
Fitness technologies will give you some
insight of that whether directly on the
app or something you can get if you dive
in to the data a little bit
further HRV is really challenging though
because there's a lot of ways to measure
it's not standardized and there's just a
lot more context we have time to get
into right now so unfortunately we're
going to have to take a little bit of a
pass on that respiratory rate is
actually quite simple you probably want
to focus at least initially on
respiratory rate over night rather than
during the day but both are acceptable
as well and again probably already
coming in any of the technologies that
you may be using to track your sleep
recovery or performance or anything else
so I'd like to focus most of our
attention here on the cardiovascular
stuff that we spent most of our time in
our conversation with and get into some
of those details right now the gold
standard to measure your V2 Max is going
to be in a laboratory with a metabolic
cart you can get this stuff in various
equations you you can use any of your
Fitness Technologies I will strongly
encourage you though that if you care
about this number if it's possible and
it may not be spend a couple of hundred
dollars and get this actually tested in
a laboratory the data are quite clear at
this point I have not yet seen really
any standard over-the-counter Fitness
technology that gets an accurate number
of your V2 Max when the number gets high
and particularly for people who are
already fairly fit if you're VX is
really low it might give you a decent
number but for folks that are kind of
moderate to highly trained it's just
really challenging to get an appropriate
estimate from a watch or a ring or
things like that perhaps those will
improve in the future in fact I quite
expect them too but as of now the margin
of error is a little bit too high for me
to be comfortable with when you care
about accuracy if you're trying to just
get a global sense they're fine um in
fact if you want to do that you can use
any number of absolutely free estimate
equations examples of this would include
something like a 2-minute step test
where you would take your heart rate
step up and down on a very small box say
12 in or so you do that cons
continuously for 2 minutes and then
measure your heart rate at the end you
can enter that score into uh an equation
and get an estimate of your V2 Max those
are scientifically validated
methodologies uh the 12-minute test ends
up being something like a mile and a
half run so you could simply in fact you
can do this if you'd like as well run a
mile and a half as fast as you can take
that time enter it into equation and get
an estimate if you have that time as
well as your heart rate you can enter it
in as well and get a more accurate
picture and so again all of these are
close we call these submaximal estimates
because they are that they are not the
direct measure so I would encourage you
again if at all possible to actually go
into a laboratory and get this measured
in addition if you do something like
that you can get a bunch of other
metrics you can't get with some some of
these estimate equations like what
percentage of fat versus carbohydrate
you're using your Anor robic and lactate
thresholds your maximum ventilation so
how much total air you can bring in and
out and a bunch of other stuff that we
talked about in the show and we'll get
into in a second again if you don't have
access to any of that that's fine use
any of those other free or extremely
lowcost options and you'll get yourself
pretty close our next eye is
interpretation so sticking with heart
rate and V2 Max as I mentioned a little
bit earlier resting heart rate will go
down as you improve Fitness but your
maximum heart rate will not really
change in fact if anything it will be
reduced because you're a little bit
older and so to State it one more time
there's no real association between
highly fit people and their maximum
heart rate and unfit people so it's not
a metric that we should be overly
concerned about of you know where is
your maximum heart rate it is relevant
to again your stroke volume but the
heart rate itself is not going to tell
you that much so not something to be
concerned about your resting heart heart
rate though or your heart rate at any
given intensity is very important so if
you're going to be running say at a
standard Pace say 7 m hour and your
heart rate at 7 miles per hour was 150
beats per minute and now a couple of
months later your heart rate at the
exact same speed is now 115 bits per
minute that would represent a
significant Improvement in
cardiovascular fitness stroke volume
would be much higher and because of that
that allows your heart rate to come down
right justing heart rate is a similar
story giving you a little bit of context
here and the reason this is top of mine
is because there's a hummingbird that
lives in my backyard and my wife and
kids look at it every single day and
they get so excited they call her mom's
Little Helper they named it squirt
actually and so they get really excited
when this little hummingbird is flying
back there because it's super fast
hummingbirds have a resting heart rate
of something like 1,200 beats per minute
it's absolutely insane so you're talking
about putting an order of magnitude on
top of almost a human mag maximum heart
rate you contrast that to a larger
animal like a giraffe an elephant or a
blue whale and you're talking about a
heart rate of something like five to six
beats per minute and so humans of course
are are somewhere in between if you were
technically to Google this you might see
something like a normal resting heart
rate is 60 to 100 beats per minute I I
am here to tell you I I cannot fathom a
situation in which somebody's resting
heart rate is over 80 beats per minute
and they are healthy and I absolutely
would not think that that would happen
to somebody who is performing at their
Max Maxum in fact I even will tell you
this is off the record this is not the
science this is me and my professional
opinion even a resting heart rate of 60
or so particularly in a man is that's
catching my eye I would like to see most
folks probably in the 40s to 50s
somewhere in the range again you might
be fine at 60 but getting a much above
60 is quite a bit high I can also
personally tell you I've worked with
plenty of athletes specifically in this
case uh several UFC fighters whose
resting heart rates were in the low 40s
if not high 30s so 37 38 40 things like
this and so that's the lowest I have
personally seen that said there are
classic stories of plenty of endurance
athletes you're talking about Elite
cyclists and cross country skiers and
marathon runners and such who are in the
low 30s the lowest I'm aware of is the
the legendary cyclist Mel induran having
a resting heart of 28 beats per minute
as far as I can tell that's the lowest
ever reported in this scientific
literature though please if you've seen
any lower uh let me know I'm sure there
are plenty of stories of anecdotes of
people uh in personal training records
and stuff who think they're lower but if
you've ever seen anything verified
scientifically I would love to see that
interpreting your V2 Max is more
interesting in my opinion because
there's a lot of components to it and so
in order to truly understand this let's
talk about how we calculate V2 Max to
begin with the easiest way in my opinion
is to think about V2 Max equals your
cardiac output multiplied by what's
called your AV V2 difference now as I've
stated cardiac output is simply your
stroke volume multiplied by our heart
rate so if we were to combine this
entire thing we would say your heart
rate multiplied by your stroke volume
which says okay how much blood am I
getting out per pump how many pumps am I
getting and I multiply that by what's
called your av2 difference now the a
stands for arterial v stands for Venus
and the O2 is oxygen so what literally
this means is what's the difference in
oxygen concentrations between the
arterial side and the Venus side
remember arteries generally go away from
your heart which means they're going to
exercising tissue and veins come back
and so what we're really looking at is
saying okay how much blood how much
Oxygen's in the blood when it leaves the
heart this is going to be the highest
concentration of oxygen
possible and how much is in the blood
when it comes back having passed through
muscle
this then directly tells you how much
oxygen your tissue extracted in the
process so to give you some numbers here
to make this easy these are not accurate
just representing the math here if you
had a 100 molecules of oxygen that left
your heart and went into your
quadriceps and then once it's gone
through the capillaries that surround
all the muscles and tissues and fibers
in your quadriceps and it went in as 100
and then it came back out the other side
and went back to the heart and lungs to
be re
oxygenated if it went in at 100 and came
out at 75 the difference between the
arterial and the Venus side is 100 minus
75 which would give you a score of 25
now what that means and I'm again I'm
using those round numbers to make this
simple you've extracted now 25% of the
oxygen that came in your system you only
got 25% of it out that's not a very good
score you want that number because it's
a multiplier to be as high as possible
so if 100 goes in I don't want 75 coming
out I want zero coming out let's say
maybe you got 10 out so now 100 went in
10 came out you extracted 90% of the
oxygen that was available to you and got
to bring it into muscle and use it for
everything we talked about earlier and
so now your avo2 difference is 90 much
higher than 25 so we get to multiply
that by our cardiac output which brings
our V2 Max even higher the easiest way
to think about V2 Max is to use What's
called the FI equation VO2 max according
to the FI equation is your heart rate
now there how many beats per minute
multiplied by your stroke volume how
much blood coming out per pump
multiplied by what's called your avo2
difference to be perfectly honest with
you the av2 difference numbers are
difficult to convey over Audio Only so
I'm going to spend most of our time on
the other side of the equation when it
comes time to interpreting your VO2 max
numbers there's a lot of charts and
papers you can use we'll provide some of
those in the show notes for you for you
I want to give you some numbers though
to give you rough context typically we
think about V2 Max in what's called a
relative term now scientists and people
that are more advanced in this field
might like to use the absolute versions
uh depending on the scenario that make
more more sense but for now let's just
stick to the relative what that means is
how many milliliters of oxygen are you
using per kilogram of body weight per
minute so you'll see them expressed as
things like your V2 Max is 50
milliliters per Kil
per minute so 50 m of oxygen per
kilogram of body weight per minute you
can kind of think about V2 Max almost on
a scale of Z to 100 and so the average
person that would kind of say walk out
of my classroom somewhat moderately
trained male or female that's you know
in the neighborhood of 170 lbs or 70
kilos something like that is probably
going to have a V2 Max around you know
35 to 45 milliliters per kilogram per
minute something in that range if you
fall below 8 18 milliliters per kilogram
per minute you're probably Crossing
below the threshold of what we call
Independence for women that's about 15
or 16 which means it's very difficult to
live independently and by yourself
because your Fitness is so low going
through basic activities of daily living
become challenging so what I'd like to
share with you is not only the normative
values but also the highest we've ever
seen in terms of V2 Max cardiac output
and stroke volume now there's so much
data on V2 Max we can actually break
this this down by age and by sex in
really specific numbers so uh if you
know your exact age you can go ahead and
look these up and these this charge but
I'll give you a couple again just to
give you Paul Park let's say you were a
female between 40 and 49 years old and
your V2 Max was 28 that would put you as
what we consider to be below average if
you wanted to go from below average to
average you'd have to go into the 32 to
36 milliliters per kilog range if you
wanted to go all the way to Elite tell
me what's the best ever you'd be needing
to surpass the mark of 47 milliliters
per kilogram per minute any of you that
are maybe older let's go ahead and jump
way down uh let's say you are 71 years
old again talking about a 71y old female
here below 18 you know you're still
above that line of Independence but it
would still be considered low you would
really want to be looking at something
like 22 to 24 to be considered above
average and then really over 36 to be
considered Elite now I know uh my friend
Peter AA likes to tell people he wants
them to be considered Elite in at least
the decade before their actual age if
not two decades before and that's a
phenomenal way to think about it so just
as that example if you were that
incredibly ambitious and vigorous
71-year-old Elite for you would be 36
milliliters per kilogram per minute the
decade before again 60 to 69 that would
be 40 but if you wanted to be that extra
person and get that double gold stamp
from from Peter you'd want to be above
46 so the difference is going from 36 to
46 would give you that Elite category
for two decades younger than you for the
men it's a similar story you just add a
little bit of the numbers to it so a
male who is say between 50 and 59 years
old above average would be 36 to 40
milliliters per kilogram per minute and
you need to be above 50 to be considered
Elite at that age
now in my personal opinion I kind of
like to say there's no excuse to be
under 50 unless you're over 50 meaning
you have no reason to be having a video
to Max of lower than 50 unless you're
over 50 years old and even then 50 to 60
I don't want you anywhere near below 50
so that's a nice number to go after uh
we'll also talk about in a second how
changeable that is and how much it
responds to various types of training
and so it's going to give you a little
bit of hope you have some room to move
there and it will respond to your
training and so there's some at the end
of the tunnel if you're looking at those
numbers and you've had a V2 Max done
recently and you're thinking oh my gosh
I am way below what Andy said there
that's fine you still have within your
capabilities to change that now while I
said that those are technically Elite
and would probably put you in the 99th
percentile they aren't necessarily the
highest we've ever seen in fact it is
very common to be much much higher than
the scores I just described so as always
I'd love to share with you what the best
in the world are it's important for us
to reset our standards and recognize and
challenge what we think is possible and
to not accept just being in the 99th
percentile let's see what is absolutely
possible in human physiology and those
no numbers and scores go far higher than
that 55 and 60 I just describ so for
many many years in history the highest
documented V2 Max that we would you know
acknowledge scientifically was from an
Austrian CrossCountry skier now this
study was was actually published about 4
years prior to him then winning a gold
medal in the Olympics and so he was
obviously a very high profile and highly
successful athlete he came in if you
know these values if not that's okay
with a hemoglobin concentration uh up
around 16.8 which is outrageous most
folks are going to be 14 or 15 or
something like that uh hemoglobin is the
molecule that carries oxygen around on
your red blood cells so innately he's
got a huge ability to do that his V2 Max
was reported to be 9 .6 m per kilogram
per minute which is incredible so that
actually stood around for a very long
time and people thought that that's
basically it again there had been talks
of people in the 92s 93s and stuff like
that but nothing had really been
independently verified whether you think
that's important or not hard to know
right until a few years later and this
is one of the most miraculous and cool
stories I ever remember being a part of
in fact I remember when this happened
live and it was fun for me getting
prepared for this show to go back and
read the updates on this individual cuz
it was such a stark and massive change
it's it was one of those LeBron James or
Tiger Woods moments uh for the endurance
and exercise physiology worlds uh the
guy came on the scene was an absolute
Phenom what I'm talking about of course
is the story of the legendary Norwegian
cyclist Oscar senson Oscar came on as an
18-year-old and I remember hearing these
murmurs coming and people were saying
some kid some 18-year-old just hit a 100
on a V2 Max score and everyone was like
no way again we've heard all these
stories before may or may not be true
and everyone was basically like okay
prove it prove it you've got to do it in
a verified way we got to send some
independent scientists out there in fact
they sent the
manufacturers for the the metabolic
heart company out to the facility that
says you need to be here you need to
verify this thing is accurate nobody
really believed it not the first time we
had heard stories like that and so of
course um actually the the team out
there that was coaching him connected
with a guy named Mike Joiner Mike is a
legendary exercise physiologist at the
male clinic um one of these people
actually who's probably potentially
published more in this area did a lot
when we were considering uh in the early
2000s whether or not a two-hour Marathon
was even physiologically possible Mike
did a lot of these calculations so
really involved in the field they
connected with Mike they published this
paper and it turns out that they were
actually able to verify um that Oscar
was able to hit a V2 Max of 96.7 ml per
kilogram per minute if you're more
familiar with absolute terms that' be an
absolute of 7.4 lers per minute just
phenomenal phenomenal record what's also
really interesting about this story is
he actually retired just a few years
later at the age of 21 or 22 I think he
had some success in competitive cycling
but perhaps not as much as one would
think given his VO2 max was so
extraordinary I think this is also an
interesting message right it tells you
this is one of the reasons why we love
sport it's just because you have some
physiological parameter you you're tall
or have some skill that doesn't
necessarily mean you're always going to
win endurance events are based on more
than just V2 Max and Sports in general
have a lot of things going on in them
besides just physiology I love
physiology I'm obsessed with it but it's
also why I love watching sports because
you never know what's actually going to
happen the world record for VO2 max for
females is also phenomenally impressive
this belongs to of course the iconic
Paula Radcliffe she had a VO2 max
reportedly about 75 milliliters per
kilogram per minute if you're unfamiliar
with Paula multiple time world record
holder in the
marathon again iconic is maybe even not
enough to describe how successful and
talented Paula was she reportedly ran
somewhere in the distance of 140 to 160
miles per week and this is actually
really cool because this is a a document
that you can go look up she had a a very
well respected and known exercise
physiologist Andy Jones he was actually
one of the gentlemen probably most
responsible for bringing beetroot juice
and Arginine and things like that onto
the scene uh from a supplementation and
nutrition perspective but Andy worked
with her for I believe almost 20 years
and was able to document her training
and her uh performance and metrics and
things like that so was able to take her
through a bunch of world records and so
has this stuff as something you can go
download and take a look at before we
move into our final category of
intervention I think it's important to
give you some context I realize many of
you are probably familiar with a
vertical jump test a 40- yard dash maybe
your One max bench press those numbers
kind of make sense perhaps these ones
they they have less context for you it's
hard to grasp how impressive they are
outside of seeing how much bigger or
higher these numbers are for world
champions relative to the rest of us the
numbers don't make a lot of sense so
what I've done is is I've made a couple
of quick calculations here to give you a
little bit of context of what it means
physiologically to have a V2 Maxis High
uh what that means in terms of how much
you're pumping throughout your system
how efficient your muscles are at
getting that in and so just as a couple
of examples want to hit you with some
fun numbers here as we talked about
earlier a standard cardiac output at
rest is something like 5 lers per minute
and remember cardiac output is heart
rate multiplied by stroke volume so if
we assume a resting heart rate of say 60
beats per minute and we wanted to get to
that number of call it 5 liters per
minute that would mean your stroke
volume would need to be somewhere in the
area of about 80 to 90 milliliters all
right now for some of you depending on
where you're at milliliters make
complete sense uh those here in America
maybe not and so I've converted that at
something in the neighborhood of like
you know just under 3 ounces and so
while you're sitting here resting every
time your heart is beating it's kicking
out about 3 ounces of blood every time
watch how high this number gets when we
get to maximal exercise in the case of
these phenomenal athletes like Paula or
Oscar we don't actually know their
stroke volume but we can run some quick
calculations and get a pretty close
estimate
Oscar would have had to be in the
neighborhood of about 225 milliliters at
his max to reach the cardiac output of
around 40 to 45 lers to give him a V2
Max uh in the 100 or so milliliters per
kilogram per minute again I know I'm
moving from liters to milliliters so run
the math yourself if you want to
challenge that number on the back end as
I said avo2 difference is really kind of
complicated so most people are probably
in the neighborhood of about 70%
extraction rate so of all the going into
tissue they're able to get about 70 of
it higher trained athletes though are
looking something more like 93 94 95%
and so the ability to extract get it
into tissue Which is far higher than the
average person in that 70 to 80% range
coming backwards into stroke volume if
we assume that he or or she is in that
neighborhood of like you know 200 to 20
25 milliliters or so um this is what
that math would look like so if we said
Oscar was call him 20 years old to make
math a little bit easier his predicted
maximum heart rate would be about 200
beats per minute if you're not familiar
with that equation if you take 220
subtract your age that gives you a very
rough and please this is just a rough
estimate of your maximal heart rate but
a a maximum heart rate of 200 beats per
minute is is maybe a little higher than
what you'd really see but not out of the
question so if we took 200 and
multiplied that by 225 that stroke
volume so the heart rate multiplied by
the stroke volume that would put us
right near that 45 L per minute Mark
again that's the highest I've ever seen
in terms of cardiac output perhaps
there's some conditioning and endurance
coaches out there that have seen higher
but but that's that's phenomenally high
in fact again many of the the best
performing endurance athletes ever are
still in 40 42 lers per minute and so
Oscar would have had to again be able to
get at least up to 200 beasts per minute
and if not if he could only say get to
190 his stroke volume would have had to
been even higher than 225
what that functionally represents for
those you know not familiar with the
metric
system 45 L per minute is just under 12
gallons of blood pumped per minute
throughout your body I'll say that one
more time 12 gallons of blood being
pumped throughout your entire body every
single minute another way to think about
that that 225 millit is around 7.5 7 .6
o so if we go back to earlier remember
when I said you're kicking out you know
something like under 3 o per contraction
now you've over doubled that number
right so you're giving you know half a
bottle of water out per pump but you're
pumping three times per second remember
your heart rate's no longer at 60 beats
per minute as in one beat per second
it's over triple that so you're beating
3.3 or so times per minute so you're not
getting out 7.6 ounces per second you're
getting that out per pump but what
you're really getting out is closer to
like 25 or 26 ounces per
second like a general water bottle is 12
to 16 ounces a large one is 20 you're
doing that entire thing every second
that you're exercising and that your
heart is beating if you were then to
extend that throughout the entire minute
it would mean you've pumped over 1,500 o
in a single minute through your heart I
don't know if and how any of that
information actually helps your life but
me personally find it just endlessly
fascinating to think about not only the
performance side of this equation right
how fast can I run a marathon and things
like that and that's really awesome and
cool but what's the physiology behind it
what does my body have to do to enable
something like that to occur and
thinking about the fact that man I'm
going to have to pump 12 gallons of
blood through my body per minute to be
able to execute on something like that
to me that's that's maybe even a bigger
Joy than seeing somebody perform a race
at a certain time both equally
impressive and fun but love to see the
physiology behind that to round this
entire story out let's move on to our
third and final eye which is
intervention in other words what can you
do about these things how much do they
change and what do I have to do to see
improvements in them if we work
backwards through this V2 Max equation
as we've talked about can we see
improvements in our avo2 difference
absolutely
how so we're primarily looking for a
couple of things one increase in
capillarization so the amount of
capillaries in our exercising muscle and
or some sort of combination of improved
mitochondrial size or content if you do
those things you'll be better at
extracting the oxygen that's coming in
into the tissue as well as utilizing it
to go through aerobic and anerobic
Recovery
metabolism back off of that we now have
stroke volume and in fact one of the
things that makes this interesting is as
we go towards maximum exercise and start
improving our stroke volume we start to
run into a little bit of a problem you
see if our heart rate is too high we
don't have enough time to fill the
ventricles and the arteries back up with
blood and so we start actually reducing
our stroke volume and so this is one of
the reasons why you would not actually
want to have your heart rate continue to
increase as a training adaptation it's
now at the point somewhere around 200
beats per minute or so
where it's compromising what's called
filling time if you don't have enough
time there we can't get enough blood in
so while you have extremely strong
tissue and you can pump a lot of the
blood out of there per pump your
ejection fraction is massive right
you're getting all the blood in the left
ventricle out of there every single time
you contract you've got to have some
physical time to actually fill it up and
so you will see adaptations in the the
heart tissue itself in fact if you look
at the actual size of the left ventricle
kind of an average number to things
about there is like 150 g or so in a
non-athlete where maybe you know upwards
of 200 in an athlete is something that
we see respond and is generally
Associated as a positive adaptation to
exercise and so we know we need to
increase the strength of the left
ventricle as a starting place if we do
that that will allow or actually produce
and result in an increase in stroke
volume so what does that mean for
training well fundamentally outside of
things like exercise technique and
timing and nutrition and all that other
stuff if we're just talking about the
background physiology we have two
Avenues or areas to push on to improve
our V2 Max we have our stroke volume and
our av2
difference so there's a lot of ways we
go about improving both of them I am of
the opinion that you need to train
across a wide spectrum of exercise
intensities to optimize both factors if
you in fact look at Classic training
logs of endurance athletes uh going back
to even what we know about Oscars
training they are typically going to
spend something like 70% or so of their
time at a low intensity what's that mean
exactly depends on the athlete but
you're probably talking about something
like between 60 to 80 maybe up to 82% of
their heart rate Peak most of their time
is there I'll explain why in a second
then you've got another additional maybe
20 to 25% of your time being spent at a
moderate intensity and typically
something like again 82 to 90 or so per
of your heart rate Peak and then three
to maybe 6% of the time at the remaining
higher heart rate so this is 92 93% or
so plus the reason I'm giving you kind
of rough guidelines there is every
scientific paper has those zones if you
will a little bit differently all kinds
of different endurance coaches
historically have set different
landmarks and so there's no exact
numbers there and so as a very guideline
I think it is very safe to assume some
split like that should be highly
effective at improving your V2 Max
what's that mean in terms of exercises
well actually it's entirely up to you V2
Max is remember depending upon how many
milliliters of oxygen per kilogram of
muscle per minute which means the more
muscles you utilize the higher the V2
Maxes uh if you were to go to get a VO2
max test done and let's say you were not
specifically trained Tred on like a
bike if you were to get that same exact
test done on a bicycle versus a
treadmill where you're running versus
cycling the score on the treadmill is
going to be about 10% or so higher than
it is on the bike and that's simply
because there's a small increasing the
amount of muscles
involved when it comes to running versus
cycling now if you were specifically
trained on the bike and you cycle a lot
that may not actually be the case and in
fact highly endurance strained folks ony
cyclists rather will score higher on a
V2 Max test on the bike than they will
on a tread mode but that really is now
coming down to test specificity
efficiency and like other things that
are that's not what we're trying to talk
about here and so generally the more
muscles involved the more oxygen being
utilized the higher that V2 Max so when
it comes to training we want to think
about the same thing the exercise mode I
don't want to say it doesn't matter it
is relevant but you have unlimited
options if you want a bike or swim or
cycle or row that's great if you don't
like any of those traditional modalities
and you want to use something like an
assault bike or pull a sled run up hill
drag something those are also incredibly
viable options it's not the exercise per
se that determines the adaptation it's
the application of the exercise right
the Body Works and Physiology works on a
principle called the said principle
which stands Sid which stands for
specific adaptation to imposed demand so
you put a demand on a
tissue to bring in and utilize oxygen at
a high rate it will adapt that specific
demand so challenging your muscles
continuously to bring in and utilize
oxygen at a rapid rate is all
fundamentally that needs to happen for
you improve that and so again the mode
of the exercise is not that big of a
deal if you are new to exercise I would
generally recommend you being careful of
exercises that involve a lot of Ecentric
action so jumping Landing because you're
going to get really sore really fast but
if not feel free to choose whatever
exercise modality or combination of them
switch it up a little bit do some
cycling do some running uphill jump in
the pool really up to
you the intensity which you do that is
more like what I just explained as I
apologized at the beginning of the
program I earlier in my life grossly
underappreciated the cardiovascular
system as a whole and I certainly
underappreciated the importance of low
intensity exercise I'll also be candid
with you here I am not as fond of Zone 2
exercise as some other folks are I don't
certainly don't think it's bad it is
good for you I just don't think you need
to be that worried about what exact Zone
you're in you want to be something
probably in that lower intensity 60 to
80ish per of your heart rate I don't
really care where your millimolars are
in any of those low intensities you're
going to be challenging the ability to
bring in and utilize oxygen over a long
period period of time look at any amount
of research on that it is very clear
steady state lower intensity exercise
especially over time 6 months to a year
is generally going to improve VO2 max
probably upwards of 5 to 10% depending
on the person the training history and
other contexts like that so it's very
very effective and something I have
absolutely Incorporated more and more
into my both my life personally as well
as my coaching practice so really
important to do that stuff on the other
end of the equation you can do things at
an extremely high intensity for a short
bout depending on the study you want to
pull here you can see things like
high-intensity intervals this could be a
combination of 30 seconds of maximal
exercise resting 30 seconds and
repeating that anywhere between like
four and 12 times can equally improve V2
max if not greater and more so than your
steady state
exercise there's a lot more context that
go into that it's not necessarily
meaning High intensity is better there
are some significant downsides and
concerns with only doing high-intensity
exercise another thing I've changed my
opinion on and so I think we want to use
high-intensity exercise there's clear
benefit
there it's fundamentally different
though than low intensity exercise so
we're challenging a different part of
the system which is why I'm going to
argue you should be incorporating both
most of the time doesn't have to be
always in all of your training but you
wouldn't want to leave either either one
of these things entirely off if the pure
goal here is to maximize
V2 reason is when you do something at a
higher intensity the point of failure in
the tissue becomes different so
extending my ability to move at a lower
or moderate intensity for a long period
of time is challenging different aspects
than it is when I ask it to introduce a
tremendous amount of fatigue so I'm now
into Anor robic metabolism when I'm
going really hard and really fast I
can't use oxygen so I'm building up a
ton of byproducts pH is being disturbed
potential damage is happening other
things are occurring CO2 is getting
extremely high and so enhancing my
ability to deal with that is a similar
thing in terms of increasing
mitochondria biogenesis so more
mitochondria higher functioning
mitochondria larger mitochondria
increasing aerobic capacity all of these
same things
occur and so again I don't want to make
the arent that one Higher intensity or
low intensity is better than another I
think you should do both I will make the
same argument for moderate intensity
while that isn't as specific and precise
in terms of what it's challenging it's
reasonable to build some of that into
your equation as well another thing
you're going to find commonly in the
research is a longer bout of intervals
this is described in a lot of different
ways a good friend of mine and an expert
in endurance physiology Joel Jameson has
talked a lot about high-intensity
continuous training hict if you're not
familiar with that stuff I would
encourage you to look it up it's very
very effective lots of different things
and tools we can pull out here one
example would be something like let's go
uh what a classic Runner would do is
something more like one M repeats so run
a mile as fast as you can this is going
to take most folks you know six to eight
or n minutes or so however long it takes
you to run that mile rest that same
amount of time so it's say one to one
work to rest ratio so 6 minutes of
running 6 minutes of rest and then you
repeat that again for a total of two or
three or perhaps four repetitions that's
a very long workout the average person
would not not be able to do that but
those of you that are not average and
are that are good to high to strong
performers listening right now that's
absolutely within your capabilities and
fact you've probably done it before it
doesn't have to be that extreme you
could use shorter durations say 2
minutes 3 minutes 4 minutes is a very
very common one you'll find in research
so four minutes of allout exercise four
minutes of recovery repeat it again two
to four times what's critical to
understand here is these work when
you're actually achieving a maximum in
that time domain so you can't do four
minutes at 70% rest for 4 minutes and do
that again that's going to burn you some
calories and has other benefits of just
making you feel better today and some
other stuff like that but in terms of
VO2 max that's probably not the most
efficient thing you can do so to
summarize all of that stuff spend a good
amount of time at a lower intensity
that's going to drive efficiency common
adaptation there since it's going to be
the highest activity you can do to
maximize utilizing fat for fuel you're
still going to be burning primarily
carbohydrates don't get that confused
but that's the best way to burn some fat
so this is typically associated with
higher metabolic
efficiency getting better at using fat
as a fuel source and things like that
it's also easy to recover from it's not
going to change your autonomic nervous
system that much so you typically don't
see uh big drops in uh HRV scores we
don't really see as much overtraining or
non-functional overreaching elevations
in respiratory heart rate other signs of
hunger fatigue not wanting to train
things like that doesn't really happen
when we spend time at lower intensities
higher intensities are phenomenal really
really really time efficient but they've
got consequences as well they're going
to be entirely or mostly anerobic which
is okay too because you'll still use the
aerobic side of the equation to recover
from that so super
important but there's a price to be paid
there people can run into problems and
you you will you're more likely to see
issues with those metrics I just
described if you're doing too much
intensity too often especially if you're
combining this with a normal stressful
life so you're doing this kind of
exercise then you're going right back
into your your day job uh you're having
difficult meetings even if they're
exciting and happy meetings you're
thinking hard you're working you're
getting back and forth and you're in a
kind of a long high stress environment
all day really really challenging on the
on the system to be in that high of a
stress at all times so other ways you
can mitigate that we can talk about
those in future episodes but just wanted
to say while high-intensity exercise is
very time efficient it's not necessarily
a free pass either low intensity is not
a free pass either it's going to leave
things on the table that you're missing
so to round all that up again I would
recommend a combination of lower
intensity moderate intensity and high
intensity training the mode of the
exercise in terms of the the what you
choose bicycle kettle bells circuit
training it's entirely up to you spin
class whatever you'd like to do
frequency can be as high or as low as
you'd like there are plenty of studies
showing kind of the higher intensity
stuff done two to three times per week
can improve V2 Max but you can also do
the lower intensity stuff every day or
combination so really you can modify
this based on your lifestyle and what's
going on and finally rest rals they're
not incredibly applicable here in fact
we've already baked them in if you're
not doing intervals then there is no
rest interval if you are um we typically
look for something like a one to one
work to rest ratio but you're welcome to
do 2: one 1:2 or any combination of that
if you train appropriately and of course
you've got all the other factors like
your nutrition and sleep and Stress
Management under control it's not
unrealistic to expect a 30 to 50%
Improvement in V2 Max after 6 to 12
months you'll find plenty of studies
that land in that ballpark the rate of
increase obviously goes down as you
become more and more trained now
candidly you don't have the ability to
improve your V to Max probably as much
as you do something like your strength
but you can improve it significantly
nonetheless you will find plenty of
studies showing even a 10 to 20%
increase in highly trained individuals
after a year in untrained folks that
probably takes about half that time so
10 to 20% Improvement in four to 6
months or so so if you know where you're
at right now you train appropriately
fairly consistently again those are
reasonable numbers to expect after a
half a year or so of training and as we
understand it the biggest limiting
factor at this point is probably the
time needed to fill the ventricles back
up with blood I know we covered a lot of
ground in this episode and I hope you
had as much fun listening to it as I did
talking about it but before we walk out
of here let's quickly recap what we
discussed most importantly we talked
about why you actually breathe how you
can pull a heart out of a living animal
and it can continue to beat on its own
and while your heart unlike any of the
rest of your muscles never gets sore
along the way of course we talked about
what your heart is why that tissue is
special and unique and how it functions
we talked specifically about your V2 Max
how to test that score uh how to know
where you are that spectrum of good
great ter Elite and then really what to
do about it at the end in covering that
stuff we also gave some hints about
things like CO2 tolerance how that
influences sleep and Recovery
respiratory rate HRV and a number of
other factors that are not directly but
highly associated with overall
cardiovascular health if you were of my
opinion when I first started my full
rate IND ex physiology and you didn't
really give cardiovascular health and
performance the credit it deserved I
hope that I've changed your mind a
little bit and warmed you up to it if
you're the opposite direction coming in
being a champion of the cardiovascular
system I hope I just gave music to your
ears and let you double or triple down
on your joy and biases towards the heart
and its importance in overall health and
physical performance thank you for
joining for today's episode our goal is
to share exciting scientific Insight
that helps you perform at your absolute
best if the show resonates with you and
you want to help ensure this information
remains free and accessible to anyone in
the world there are a few ways that you
can support first you can subscribe to
the show on YouTube Spotify and apple
and on Apple and Spotify you can leave
up to a five-star review given that
we're a new podcast subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot second please check out our sponsors
the show would not exist without them
and they really are exceptional products
and services and then finally you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it if you have any
content questions or suggestions
please put those in the comment section
on YouTube I really do try to read these
and see what you have to say I use my
Instagram and Twitter also exclusively
for scientific communication so those
are great places to follow along for
more learning my handle is Dr Andy
Galpin on both platforms thank you for
listening and never forget in the famous
words of Bill Bowerman if you have a
body you're an athlete